Guide to the Michael Roemer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Michael Roemer papers
1948-2009
MS 1837
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14.75
(19 boxes)
The papers consist of drafts, screenplays, notes, school papers, poems, writings by and about Michael Roemer, and documents regarding publication.
Roemer, Michael, 1928-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Michael Roemer, 2004, 2006, and 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Michael Roemer, filmmaker and professor at the Yale School of Art, was born in Germany in 1928. He left Germany during World War II and lived in England until 1945 when he emigrated to the United States. He attended Harvard University and made his directorial debut in 1949 with A Touch of the Times. Following graduation, he made educational films and documentaries before making his first fictional film, Nothing But a Man, in 1964. Nothing But a Man earned two awards at the Venice Film Festival. In addition to making feature films, Roemer has continued to make documentaries, including Dying (1975), a film about several terminally ill cancer patients.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of drafts, screenplays, notes, school papers, poems, writings by and about Michael Roemer, and documents regarding publication.
Motion picture producers and directors; Roemer, Michael, 1928-
- Writings and Other Materials, 1948-2003
  - Act of God, Circa 1998 (Box 1)
  - Divertissement, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Ellen, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Famous Long Ago, Circa 1988-1990 (Box 1–2)
  - Famous Long Ago, Circa 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - The Flop, 1949-1952 (Box 2)
  - Harry, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Haunted, Circa 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - The Heart of Harry, Circa 1957 (Box 2)
  - Losing Emily, Circa 1984 (Box 3)
  - Emily, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Emily Lost and Found, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
  - Mr. Lincoln, 1954 (Box 4)
  - The Last Frontier, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Nothing But a Man, Circa 1963 (Box 4)
  - Pilgrim Farewell, Circa 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - A Place in Sunset, Undated (Box 4)
  - The Plot Against Harry, Undated (Box 4)
  - Sneaking into Eden scene notes, Circa 2001 (Box 5)
  - The Sprung Heart, Undated (Box 5)
  - Stone My Heart, 1972-1988 (Box 5)
  - Stone My Heart notes, Circa 1972 (Box 6)
  - Stone River Romance, 1957 (Box 6)
  - A Touch of the Times, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - Vengeance is Mine, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Telling Stories, Circa 1995 (Box 7)
  - Writing by and about Michael Roemer, 1948-2003 (Box 7)
  - Mortal Longing notes, Undated (Box 8)
  - Charles and Charlie, Undated (Box 8)
  - Notebooks on American architecture, Undated (Box 8)
  - The Heart of Harry, 1958 (Box 8)
  - The Power of Darkness, 1955 (Box 8)
  - Passage to Paradise, 1949 (Box 8)
  - Poems, Undated (Box 8)
  - Heartbreak House, "Introduction: A Note on Literary Theories", 1948-1949 (Box 8)
  - An Innocent Beginning, Undated (Box 8)
  - Ellen, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 8)
  - Unidentified screenplay, Undated (Box 8)
  - Contracts, 1963-1979 (Box 9)
  - Act of God, Losing Emily, Mortal Longing, Stone My Heart, 1995-1997 (Box 9)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 9)
  - "Hey Rockefeller", Undated (Box 9)
  - Notes for Stone My Heart, Undated (Box 9)
  - Mortal Longing, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Lecture notes, 1977-1996, undated (Box 9)
  - Correspondence and drafts of article on Charlie Chaplin, 1973-1977 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, unopened, 1972-1978, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Reviews of Dying, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Notes for Sad But Funny, Undated (Box 10)
  - Notes for Sneaking into Eden, Undated (Box 10)
  - Heartbreak House, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Poems, Undated (Box 10)
  - A Collection of Bunce Court Memories, Undated (Box 10)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 10)
  - Writings by Michael Roemer, 1960-1964 (Box 10)
- Additional Materials, 2003-2005; Accession 2007-M-013
  - Been Here and Gone, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Home Body, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2-14)
  - Losing Emily notes, Circa 2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sneaking Into Eden scene notes, Circa 2003 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
- Additional Materials, 2002-2004; Accession 2012-M-038
  Scope and Contents
  The 2012-M-038 addition to the Michael Roemer papers includes drafts, notes, and scenes from the screenplay Been Here and Gone. Drafts include handwritten edits and marginalia.
  - Drafts
    - First Draft, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Second Draft, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      General
      The folder includes notes for Sneaking into Eden.
    - Final 2004 Draft (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - New Story, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - New Story, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Orignal Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scenes and Moments, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Scene Sheets, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Additional Materials, 2007-2009; Accession 2013-M-030
  This accession includes drafts and manuscript copies of screenplays for Michael Roemer's films, Bed Rock and Home Body, as well as original notes pertaining to each film.
  - Home Body (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Screenplay, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Draft, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Original notes, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    - Original notes, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Bed Rock, 2009
    - Screenplay, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Original notes, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
    - Original notes, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)